hi I'm Bonnie and I'm recording this
from all dolor the home of all the lower
soul when Sugata Mitra first coined the
term soul he meant it a self-organized
learning environment and all the Lord we
like to think of it as self-organizing
learning experience because that's what
we're offering we're offering young
adults an opportunity to come together
work collectively work on an individual
project take advantage of this beautiful
environment that we're located in a
western part of Connecticut and learn
how to self-organize their own learning
experiences to make them rich and
profound and proposal now ever since we
launched our website last month than
having a lot of inquiries from all over
the world people really wanting to know
a little bit more about me about what my
vision is and what my educational
philosophy is so this video is an
attempt to connect on that level and
kind of give you a sense of how all the
lower soul came into being and what we
would really hope we can make of it in
2006 I went to a conference where the
keynote speaker was Steven Scott Glenn
he's a very dynamic speaker and he told
a story about Einstein and Einstein's
predictions and visions for the future
pretty much in the time period we're
living now and Einstein said that in the
future machines would take care of a lot
of the knowledge base work that we do
now or we had done in the past just like
machines take care of a lot of
repetitive physical work for us Einstein
saw that knowledge itself would become
in the future like data was for him then
there was organizing storing and
retrieving data was the work of
computers and
a what we're seeing with smarter and
smarter computers and the development of
artificial intelligence and the Semantic
Web and crowdsourcing and having
computers learned from collective
engagement with people what we're seeing
is that machines are being able to be
very confident in organizing storing and
retrieving knowledge so in the past they
exclusively machines exclusively worked
with data and it required people to use
the data to make into knowledge systems
but today we're finding as I as an Isaan
Feinstein predicted that machines are
getting increasingly better than us at
organized storing and retrieving
knowledge so this has huge implications
it has huge implications for students
entering college at this time in terms
of what are going we are going to be the
careers available to them so the
implication that means for me today is
that our responsibilities as adults and
educators is to support the development
of skills in young adults that machines
can't do that our responsibility is to
cultivate new capacities perhaps in many
instances in human development that are
beyond the range of technology at this
moment and then everything moves along
so that was one of the first really
important signposts for me back in 2006
in 2006 in that same keynote speech
Stephen Glen said that Einstein was very
fascinated with the rate of knowledge
throughout you know recent history in
that in the past for example my parents
parents knowledge doubled so slowly that
the only responsibility parents and
cheers had was to reproduce the
knowledge that they had been given and
make sure that that was adequately
passed on to their children fast forward
to when I was in college it seemed to me
that knowledge was doubling so rapidly
that by the time you got into college
you were faced with research agendas
into the unknown and recently I heard a
man speak about the kind of pickle that
children are in in terms of the fact
that when there by the time they receive
all the knowledge in a certain
discipline then that knowledge is
already obsolete and so that they're
faced with skills that they haven't
learned so if you're graduating from
college and you have all this knowledge
and even in many of the sciences you
have to go on to post doc and docx drill
so you might spend 30 years in an
institution where you're just receiving
knowledge but then by the time you've
accumulated all that knowledge then the
research has really advanced way forward
and so it's really hard for children at
that stage or adults at that stage to
make the transition to where they're
doing research where they're asking
questions of the unknown so that was a
second sign post in that keynote speech
that really got me to thinking and then
the third thing that's Stephen a Glenn
said in the keynote speech was that
again the rate of knowledge is
developing so fast that now knowledge
doubles faster than a generation I read
something the other day that knowledge
doubles in less than a year so if we
really take that to heart what what that
is saying is that by the time children
are born and into our responsibility
then we don't know what to teach them we
we are way behind the curve ball here
and so knowledge is doubling so fast
that we are in the
situation where we are not only teaching
our children skills to face an unknown
future but in unknowable future and that
had a really big impact on me so we have
these three aspects number one that
machines are going to be able to
organize store and retrieve knowledge
better than humans so that humans have
to develop capacities way ahead of the
technological curve number two that
research is requires so much received
knowledge that by the time you actually
internalize all those knowledge you
number one are way behind the curve and
number two don't have the skills for
doing action inquiry into the unknown
for innovation in an invention in number
three that educators and teachers and
parents are in the situation of having
to design an educational system and
having to support their children in the
capacity of creating capabilities for
them to fix not only an unknown future
but an unknowable future and I think we
really really really need to take that
to heart that we need to stop thinking
that our children need received
knowledge not only do they not need it
but that can be handled by machines but
that it is doing them a disservice and
the third point is that we need to take
on the responsibility of identifying
what are the capabilities that our
children need to face an unknown and
unknowable future to talk to them like
that to say we don't know what your
future is going to be like what we can
do is support your own growth in the
capacities that you will need to face an
unknown
future recently I've been thinking about
how special and innovative and creative
young adults are and I've been going
around the country doing workshops on
inside practice and inevitably when
there are intergenerational people in my
workshop it is very clear that young
adults would say 35 and younger have a
completely different mindset a
completely different understanding of
how of change in the world how change
happens the kinds of process
methodologies that are important to them
and I'm not sure that this is schooled
in them I think that this is a
evolutionary leap and I'll tell you why
my research has shown me that one of the
most significant changes or significant
situations we are dealing with today in
terms of this educational and
intergenerational aspect of our
situation is that children are now born
into a world that's so technologically
advanced that this makes a huge
difference in how they come to think
about reality so for example I grew up
before I was grew up in a school system
before there were personal computers
I've seen the development of personal
computers over time I've learned from
the beginning in both in business and in
school and I've seen how how the web has
changed over the last ten years so for
me this has a the internet is a kind of
a relative or a contingent aspect of
reality I remember what it was like
before but for children who are now
thrown into the world where a digital
world
the world of digital technology in the
internet in collective intelligence this
is not a contingent aspect of their
world this is the real world and so that
creates a situation where the world
feedbacks to them in a much different
way than it did to us and this creates
actual evolutionary leap in the
cognitive architecture of our children
so this is another situation that I
think as educators we have to take to
heart and we have to design education
now for children that in a certain sense
in the context that they're worn
actually smarter than us that they have
insights into this world that we do not
have simply by the fact of this
thoroughness this thrown into a world
that is different than the world we
experienced as children so I like to
tell children that they are penguins and
it's a little story I wanted to share
with you there's this great documentary
called march of the penguins you
probably have seen it and most people
remember the part of the story where the
Penguins take the Long March and deep
into the Antarctic and they pair up and
the female lays an egg and then the egg
gets passed to the male and females make
the long march to the sea to feed and
then in this in the early spring the
females make the long march back the
chicks are born they exchange they find
their mate they exchange their chick and
the males make the long march to the sea
because they're starving so most people
remember the story for the profound
challenges of parenthood and the
responsibilities so but for me the most
surprising and the thing that stuck with
me the most was at the point then that
the the mothers are now feeding their
chicks just from the storage
of food that they had been eating when
they were in the sea and the chicks are
growing in the and the mothers are
starting to starve to death so then at a
certain point they make the long march
to the sea back to feed and the
interesting things is the chicks wait
they're all the same generation they're
all cousins and they wait and they wait
and they wait and what they don't know
is no one's coming back for them so this
is extraordinary because in the movie
you see they're all the chicks are
getting hungry and restless and they all
kind of like congregate and move around
nervously and then all of a sudden
there's this kind of like
self-organizing scene happening and the
natural born leaders start to get
together in little groups and it's like
a congress and they and they they kind
of like talk to each other and it really
looks like they're making decisions and
the whole colony kind of self organizes
as if they're the central meaning of
this generation and then that at some
point some inner knowing kicks in and
then that little Congress starts to lead
and they make the march to the sea and
at each point where there's challenges
or maybe fissures or water holes or some
dangers then that little Congress gets
together like trying kind of
collectively making a decision and they
move forward until they get to the sea
and this is a generation that has never
made the march it's all from an inner
knowing led by natural born leaders they
get to the sea they've never seen the
sea before and in the last scenes of the
movie the same kind of initiation
happens where the Congress starts to
walk into the water and they get to like
cackling to each other and then finally
someone dies and then the next one the
next
one and that becomes a generation that
lives together so I like to think of the
generations that are born today as
penguins because of this rapid advance
of both technology and knowledge
building in a sense they're born left
alone they are born to self-organize
they are in a situation where they have
to find each other find their natural
born leaders self-organized and move
into an unknown future from some kind of
deep inner knowing that we as educators
teachers and parents need to learn how
to cultivate and for them and how to
support the cultivation of that so that
is what for me over the last 12 years or
so has been a progression progressive
research inquiry and understanding into
what what do we need to be as educators
adults and parents to really support
children into transforming their own
future and I think this is an essential
responsibility that we have at this time
in history
so now what I want to do is try to give
you a little idea of some of the ways
that we have organized this first summer
soul experience in order to address some
of that larger vision I have this little
diagram I made this morning which I hope
you can see
so we've designed the experience the
learning experience at all the lower
around three primary modes of
educational experience and I see this as
a generative process that that this
process enables improvement in this
process which enables improvement in
this process it really generates a whole
learning experience so one part one
stream of the experience is has to do
with research the ability to come up
with novel questions about that are not
that are not knowns and to start a
process of active inquiry and research
in a way that moves that question along
and the way that we support the research
of the student is through insight
practice because you can't ask questions
of the unknown without having at least
some insight some insight as to a
hypothesis or a proposition or a
relevant question and that what that
looks like primarily is collective
insect we do collective insight practice
here at at all the lore all the lore is
the home of all dolor insight Center
students engage in what I call
contemplative science because it's a
science to do research but the
contemplative aspect of it is the
ability to watch into compote
contemplate and be self-reflective of
one's inside process and why does it
matter so this generates novel questions
and novel approaches to a research
project so we have contemplative science
collective insight practice and the
research the other process stream is a
project stream so in order to do the
research it needs to be designed into a
project so a project could be a
multimedia project it could be an
interview project it could be a research
traditional academic research project
working through the internet it could be
a building project in the actual
physical project to answer some
questions and experimental set set up so
we have a project stream now the project
stream one of the skills that you need
to cultivate to support a project stream
is embodied leadership because with a
project you have to start to access and
gather resources and you're not going to
do that by just having contemplative
insight you need some embodied
leadership you need to go out in the
world and interview people you need to
go out into the world and get resources
for your experiment or your built
project and that projects inevitably
create a living center or a community of
practice so that this process during
is the project embodied leadership in
the community the community that you're
leading in an embodied way in order to
achieve your project so those are quite
academic and scientific and challenging
in a cognitive intellectual way but the
third process term I think has gotten
increasingly important and it's
something that's left tradition left out
of almost all educational design and
that is practice or practical or a
practicum so you can't just do a project
all of a sudden you're going to do it
once it just shows up now that's true in
institutional situations where the
institution will throw resources and
support and really do all the leadership
you can give the student the the sense
or at least the false sense that the
project is being led by them but the
real way that research projects and
action gets done in the world we know
requires a lot of practice and when
students are robbed of the challenge of
practice they are robbed of the
opportunity to develop the skill set
that they need to face an unknown future
so practice I've underneath practice I
put echo awareness and certainly here at
all the Lord we mean ecological
awareness because designing and doing
practice in the in the new world has to
do with being ecologically aware but I
also mean it in terms of systems view or
ecological systems view because if you
have a systems view of your practice
then it's going to inform better inform
and better generate or engineer or
design your project so the practice is
of echo awareness and how things fit
into this
system and to really bring that down
into your life skills so that that being
ecologically aware of the whole entire
system both human and non-human as a
practice and making that real right down
in terms of your life school skills is
the practice that makes the project
practical so those are the three streams
that are all the lower soul is built
upon and these three are seen as
generating and self-organizing a
profound learning experience we can look
at each one of these three streams in a
different way so that for example this
stream contemplative science being the
core which generates insight into the
research I put as a stream of
understanding so the goal of this is
understanding in the skill or the
competency that it intends is clarity of
purpose so you can see how these all
work to build more clarity of purpose
and it's the stream of understanding so
what are some of the particulars in the
street clarity of purpose on deriving
meaning being able to make these are
more like core capacities being able to
derive meaning make important and
relevant distinctions discovering
patterns and looking for innovation not
to just for Pete what's been done before
in the project stream here we have at
the core the community and it which
requires the embodied leadership to
manifest your project and I call that
the leading stream to leave to be like a
project manager and the capacity that
this is cultivating is adequate
participation so in order to gain
insight into your research to really
understand there's a certain level of
participation that is required enough of
a real-life project enough leadership
enough community adequate participation
in your project is the capacity that is
being cultivated in that stream and if
we look at core skills the ability to
its enactment skills the ability to take
a vision and enact it in the real world
the ability to do action inquiry and all
of these can be looked at in much more
detail and another core skill is to
inspire people to be inspirational
because you need a community to resource
your project so those would be some core
skills that are addressed through this
experiential stream of leading and the
last stream which is the practice dream
I say that that's the stream of creating
but there's something physical something
very practical and physical left in the
world so we have on life skills as the
basic fundamental orientation toward a
creative life for actually creating your
the structures of your own life's a very
practical
Stream hear the echo awareness that your
life is nested inside a larger system
and systems of systems including human
and non-human systems and that that it's
cultivated through long-term process and
the capacity that Steve being developed
in the creating stream I call
sensitivity for conditions and this is
also something that is being left out in
education today that students can have a
lot of good ideas and a lot of resources
but they're not sensitive to real-life
conditions it's relatively impractical
they can't they can't they can't discern
the subtle changes in appreciation or
relevance or meaningfulness and so
sensitivities to conditions I think is a
very critical capacity for us to
cultivate in our children as the core
skills and would be being able to create
a method to understand systems to have
some design skills and to be inventive
so this is the process dreams generative
stream of all the Lord's self-organizing
learning experience